Speaker 1: It's been over five years, 65 months of above 2% inflation. But if we couldn't get down to two when oil prices were falling, how the hell are we going to get down to two when they're rising? We've been lied to by the government and we're continuing to be lied to.
Speaker 2: All prices are going to keep going up because the government is going to keep creating inflation because politically they've got no alternative. They can't accept the reality. Look out because there could be some serious carnage in the bond market and then in the stocks
Speaker 2: market.
Well, the
Speaker 3: big news
since I recorded my
Speaker 4: podcast on Friday is the escalation of the Iran war over the weekend.
Speaker 4: And the impact that that's had on forcing commodity prices to continue their surge. In fact, oil prices almost hit $100 a barrel in Brent today.
They
Speaker 5: got about to $99.50. West Texas trades at a bit of a discount. But we closed the day over $94 a barrel. And, of course, diesel
Speaker 4: continues its record run.
But
Speaker 4: it's not just oil. I mean, oil makes a lot
Speaker 5: of headlines, but look at copper. Copper is a key industrial metal that hit another all-time record high today. Now, we backed off that record by the close, still up, I think, 1.3% at $6.76 a pound intraday.
Speaker 5: No, I mean, copper, it just updated 682.35 is the last quote I'm getting on Bloomberg for copper. I saw copper earlier today trading above $6.85 per pound. Copper is up close
Speaker 1: to 60%.
Speaker 1: just since Trump took office. And he's been in office for less than two years. And you've got almost a 60% move in copper. But you know, despite this move, copper prices are actually cheap when you price them in
Speaker 5: real money. A lot of people look at the gold-copper ratio. I look at it, and there have been a lot of people who thought that, well, gold's gonna fall in order to bring the ratio
Speaker 5: into balance because copper has been very low relative to gold. Some people thought, well, gold is going to come down to meet copper. I think it's the other
Speaker 1: way around. Copper is going to go up to meet gold because right now,
Speaker 5: if copper gets back to its historic average or in modern times,
if
Speaker 1: gold stays around 4,400, which is where it is now, and it's not going to stay at 4,400, but assuming it did,
Speaker 1: Copper would have to rise to over $11 a pound. That's another 60% rise from where we are now for copper not to
be
Speaker 6: expensive, just to be normal price. Because again, gold is real money. Everything you buy with funny money, with Federal Reserve
Speaker 1: notes, costs more.
but
Speaker 1: it's not because the goods are getting more expensive. It's because the currency that you're using to buy the goods is becoming less valuable. Now, if you're using real money to buy stuff, if you've got gold, well, then you don't see that. You see prices
Speaker 6: falling, including for copper. You get a great deal now on
Speaker 7: copper if you're buying it with gold, not if you're using the government's inferior fiat currency.
But
Speaker 7: copper prices have a long way to go when you measure them in terms of real money. Now, of course, this is a moving benchmark. Gold's not going to stay at $4,400. Gold is going higher, which means copper is going to stay at $4,400.
Speaker 7: is going a lot higher. But copper is just one metal. The same thing is going to be happening with nickel, zinc, all these industrial metals, tungsten, cobalt, everything is going to get more expensive. And it's not just metals. And it's not just energy. It's agricultural commodities. And look at how these stocks are performing. Look at the copper stocks today. I'm not going to go over them by name, but look at these stocks hitting 52-week highs.
Speaker 7: And the ones that haven't, you know, we're still up big and they're going to move up. Agriculture names are going up. Soaring
Speaker 5: copper prices and soaring oil prices are not consistent with a Fed that is still believing
Speaker 6: that inflation is headed down to 2%. Why would that be?
If
Speaker 6: inflation didn't even go down to 2%, and again, I'm not talking
Speaker 5: about real inflation, which is the expansion of the money supply. I'm talking about the CPI, which the government likes to point to, right? Consumer prices. But if consumer prices never got down to where they were rising at the Fed's 2% target, man, it's been over five years, 65 months of above 2% inflation. But if we couldn't get down to two
Speaker 1: when...
oil
Speaker 1: prices were falling, how the hell are we going to get down to two when they're rising? And,
you know,
Speaker 1: I keep hearing the
Speaker 5: president's, you know, yes men, you know, Scott Bessett on the Sunday morning shows confidently
Speaker 1: saying that when this Iran war is over, don't worry, oil is going to be $50 or $40 a barrel. I mean, this guy just lies. I mean, that's what Not everybody in the Trump administration does.
Speaker 1: I guess they're told a lie, and that's what they do because the whole administration is based on a lie. It's one lie after another. One of the lies is that, you know, this war is going to end.
Speaker 6: There's no end in sight. The Iran war began over six months ago. It started at the end of February. It's almost six and a half months ago.
Speaker 6: I think we're further away from victory now than we were when we first dropped the bombs. And if you remember, Trump said this was going to be, you know, a simple operation where it was going to be over in two weeks. The whole regime was going to topple. We were going to have regime change. We were going to liberate Iran. It was going to be a cakewalk. Well, it's over six months and we're actually in worse shape than we were.
But
Speaker 6: Iran is in much better shape because they've already taken the worst, I think, that we that we're going to have. I mean, we've already bombed everything. We blew up their
Speaker 8: Navy. Right. Trump keeps bragging about how their beautiful ships are on the bottom of the ocean. So we sank their ships. We blew up a lot of their missiles. We
blew
Speaker 6: up a lot of their military targets. All right. Now what? I mean, they're still there. The regime is in power.
Speaker 6: Yeah,
Speaker 7: there are different guys because we killed the other guys, but now they got the new guys. But it's it's the same regime. It's not regime change. But at this point, I mean, we're done. I mean, I said this
from day
Speaker 7: one. You go back and listen to my podcast from the day this war started.
Speaker 7: Not only did I say that it was wrong from a legal and constitutional perspective, because it's another war that we never declared. Congress didn't declare it. The president just got us involved. But
I also
Speaker 7: thought that it was not going to end the way we were being promised. Not, you know, because I'm, you know, some kind of genius at military strategy. I just, you know, have heard this before. Been there, done that.
Speaker 7: I know that every time politicians promise that we're gonna have a quick war in the Middle East, it never happens. It didn't happen with Iraq, it didn't happen with Afghanistan. All of these military interventions, they never go the way they're planned. It always takes a lot longer and we achieve a lot less. And I knew that
Speaker 7: nothing was going to change. I mean, I remember I said, I hope I'm wrong. I hope this time Trump actually pulls it off.
Speaker 5: But I knew that it was a mistake to go into the Middle East. And up until Trump
Speaker 6: declared war on Iran, we were on the same page. He agreed with me. I mean, and during his first term, he stayed out of this. And during his campaign for a second term,
He
Speaker 6: promised no wars, no more forever wars, no getting involved in the Middle East. He kept talking about how the biggest mistakes that were made by Obama or by Biden had to do with getting
Speaker 1: involved in the Middle East. And, of course, he also called out George Bush for Iraq.
Speaker 1: So he went against the Republican establishment and the whole military industrial complex.
So a
Speaker 1: lot of people who voted for Trump voted for him because of his anti-war stance. So I knew that this was going to be a political problem for Trump as well. Every investor understands counterparty risk. When you deposit money in a bank, it's not really your money anymore. It's a claim on the bank. Most people never apply that logic to their passwords. They reuse the same one everywhere. They trust some companies
Speaker 1: server to keep it safe and then that company gets hacked now their one password is everyone's password that is a single point of failure and you built it yourself here's what i'd want instead something closer to self-custody proton pass stores your passwords pass keys and credit cards under zero knowledge end-to-end encryption proton itself cannot read what is in your vault
Speaker 1: It generates a unique, strong password for every account. So one breach stays one breach. It auto-fills your logins on your phone, your laptop, whatever browser you're using. And here is the part I find clever. Instead of handing your real email to every website that asks for it, ProtonPass creates an alias. If that alias starts getting spam, you just kill it. Switching from your browser or another password manager takes one click. Go to Proton.me,
that's P-R-O,
Speaker 1: T-O-N dot M-E slash Peter, and you get 50% off, there's a 30 day money back guarantee. So the downside is zero. Stop trusting a claim, own the vault. That's Proton dot me slash Peter. And by the way, again, I don't, I hate to always just toot my own horn. I'm getting stuff right. But now in the betting markets, for the first time, the Democrats are favored to win the Senate.
Speaker 1: winning in the midterms. Now, winning the House is pretty much a lock. I mean, the odds are better than 90 percent. They've never been higher than they are right now. But up until now, the Republicans were favored to hold on to the Senate. And
now the
Speaker 1: odds are
Speaker 6: slightly that they're going to lose the Senate and
Speaker 6: despite some of the crazy candidates that they're going to have on the
Speaker 1: ballot. I mean, the Democrats are their own worst enemies. That's the only thing the Republicans got going for them is how bad the Democrats are. If the Democrats were just normal Democrats, they wouldn't have a chance. But because now they've got such far radical Democratic socialists, that's the only chance that
The
Speaker 1: Republicans have by saying, look, I know we're bad, but we're not as bad as them. Right. So vote for us as the lesser of two evils. That that's their only shot. It's not that they have anything positive to sell. All they have to do is convince people that it will be even worse if
they go with
Speaker 1: the Democrats. But but that's not a way to win an election. But I knew that was another reason that I didn't want the the war.
And of
Speaker 1: course, I just don't like war in general. I think it's a mistake. I think that we should try to resolve things through diplomacy, not through war. And I never believed
Speaker 2: the threats. I never believed the weapons of mass destruction. And I never believed that Iran was the nuclear
Speaker 7: threat that it was held out to be, especially since I've been hearing that stuff for 50 years.
like
Speaker 7: they're they're they're right around the corner from a a nuclear weapon yeah well they've been right around the corner for years decades so clearly that has not been the case we've been lied to by the government and we're continuing to be lied to no i i pointed this out trump and his uh guys in his administration
every time i
Speaker 7: hear them talk about the economy they're lying every time
And I
Speaker 7: know they're lying because I understand the economy. I mean, I'm not a military expert or anything like that, and there's a lot of things I don't necessarily know, but I know the economy and I know they lie about that. And a lot of the lies are very obvious because you just look at the statistics and they're completely
Speaker 1: lying about them. And they lie to embellish Trump's accomplishments about how great everything is under Trump, right? And so these are just lies,
but,
If
Speaker 1: they're lying when
it comes to
Speaker 1: the economy, why would they be telling us the truth when it comes to the Iran situation? They wouldn't. I mean, once you're a liar, you're a liar. It's not like you just lie about certain things. If you're willing to lie, well, then you're going to lie about everything if it's convenient. If you're honest, then you have to tell the truth, even if the truth could get you in trouble.
But once
Speaker 1: you've crossed the line to lying, well, you're not going to stop.
So
Speaker 1: I'm sure that they're lying about everything. Even the stuff I don't know is a lie. I assume it's a lie. I don't know why they would ever tell the truth, especially if the truth is not good. They don't want us to hear that, right? It's like Jack Nicholson from "A Few Good
Men." They
Speaker 1: all know we can't handle the truth. It's much easier to give us a lie when the truth is so bad.
So all
Speaker 1: we're getting is these lies, but if you go back to what I said, I said we were going to lose this war, and the reason I said we were going to lose this war was because I said Iran was going to win, and
by that I
Speaker 1: didn't mean that they were going to kill more Americans than we killed more Iranians, no, I knew that we had the bigger military, I said they win by surviving.
They
Speaker 1: win by standing up to the great Satan, which they did. They took our best. We dropped all our bombs. We dropped all our missiles. And they're still there. They're still standing. And now we've already switched from a military war, even though some of the military stuff escalated
Speaker 2: over the weekend. That was part of the problem. But we're now focusing more
Speaker 1: on an economic war.
Speaker 1: We're waging this economic war, which we're also going to lose, by the way. We're not going to win this war either. But I hear Scott Bessett talk about this or Trump talk about it. It's going to be the greatest issue.
Speaker 1: economic war ever that we are going to come down on Iran like no country has ever been hit before. It's going to be the greatest wave of economic sanctions. We're going to strangle them. And, you know, look, look
at what
Speaker 1: we did to Cuba. Cuba's still there. Yeah.
I don't
Speaker 1: know if this is going to be worse than what what, you know, the embargoes and blockades and all the stuff that we did with Cuba.
Speaker 1: But, you know, Castro, you know, we never got rid of him despite all of our efforts. But apparently this is going to be worse. This is going to be an even
Speaker 7: bigger thing. And
I think
Speaker 7: all this is a lie. I mean, a lot of it is based on the belief that the rest of the world is going to cooperate because we've threatened them with these secondary sanctions. They're not going to believe that. They all know that whatever we threaten, it's all BS.
I
Speaker 7: mean, a perfect example I talked about on my last podcast when instead of threatening Iran, Trump threatened the Fed. He threatened the Fed by saying that he was going to basically destroy the entire U.S. economy if the Fed didn't cut rates when the
probability of
Speaker 7: a rate hike went up. In fact, as of now, the probability is about 60 percent.
that
Speaker 7: the Fed's going to hike rates next week. Now, I still don't think they're going to do it. They should. In fact, they should raise rates by a lot more than the 25 basis points that people would expect. But when Trump saw those jobs numbers, apart from claiming credit for how great the numbers were, which they really weren't, even though they were a beat. And again, I think by the time
the dust
Speaker 7: settles, they're going to end up being revised to a miss. But I discussed that on my last podcast.
Trump
Speaker 7: immediately said, "Look, the Fed needs to cut rates because we deserve low rates and cut rates. And if you don't do it, we're going to call off trade. We're gonna embargo all trade with all countries that have trade surpluses, which of course would hurt us." And in fact,
Speaker 5: everything that Trump threatens with respect to trade, everything he threatens, the sanctions, the tariffs, the biggest losers are
Speaker 1: Americans.
Speaker 1: That's one of the reasons that the threats don't work, because Trump would harm
Speaker 6: the U.S. economy more than the economies of the nations that he's threatening.
Speaker 5: So the Fed knows that Trump is bluffing, that, you know, he's not going to carry through. And I think the rest of the world knows
Speaker 6: that they can continue to do business with Iran and there's nothing that we're going to do
about it
Speaker 6: because we don't have the cards.
If we
Speaker 6: if we if we do embargoes, if we if we outright ban trade, it's going to be even worse. And I'm going to get to that because
Speaker 5: there's a lot of stuff I want to talk to about trade, but just getting getting back to the the war. So
the
Speaker 6: war is not working. We are losing this war. Even the administration
now
Speaker 1: admits that.
Speaker 1: There's no nuclear deal anywhere in sight. So it's not even about the nuclear deal. I don't even know what it's about. Maybe it's about trying to reopen the Straits of Hormuz, which were completely open before the war. Our real goal is just to get back to the status quo from before we started a war that we never should have started. But now we're not going to do that.
Speaker 1: Because Iran is not
Speaker 5: going to give this up. Iran is going to control that strait. They're going to have a toll and they're going to collect a lot of money and their clout in the region is going to grow. They are going to be a more powerful economic force than before we
Speaker 1: declared war against them. And probably that means eventually they'll have a there'll be a bigger military threat. They may be a lesser military threat now.
Speaker 1: Um, but that doesn't mean they won't be a lesser threat later because they'll have more money to, to build even, even more weapons in the future because we're putting them in a better economic position and we are driving our enemies closer
Speaker 2: together. Uh, China, you know, is going to be having a better, uh, relationship, uh, you know, with, with, with Russia and a lot of these countries are now, you know, uh,
Speaker 1: getting,
further
Speaker 1: distancing themselves. Look, we know the Norwegian Sovereign Wealth Fund announced a major sale. I think like 60 billion worth of U.S. Treasuries. It's going to be unloading. Obviously, they're going to be buying something else with it. But the world is moving away from the U.S. dollar. We have alienated so many of our friends, particularly
Canada,
Speaker 1: Canada, look what's happening there today. And I guess this is a good
Speaker 2: point to segue into trade. Although, wait, before I do that, though, what's happening
Speaker 1: with the escalation of the war is helping to drive up these commodity prices like oil, like copper, like agricultural commodities. All of this means much higher consumer prices when voters are at the polls. Just driving to the polls is going to be a lot more...
Speaker 1: expensive than it was when they voted in
Speaker 2: 2024 inflation is going to be the number one issue in 2026 just like it was the number one issue in 2024 except now the inflation shoe is on the other foot in 2024 everybody blamed the democrats for the
Speaker 1: inflation that's why trump was able to win he won by promising to lower prices on day one
Speaker 1: Well, prices are going to be much higher in November 2026 than they were in November 2024. And so who are the voters going to blame for that? They are going to blame Trump, the man who promised lower prices. And they're going to blame every Republican who's running down ticket. And what's the solution going to be? The Democratic Socialists. Why? They're promising lower prices.
And they're, of
Speaker 1: course, blaming the high prices on greedy capitalists, ripping you off. But they can also blame it on the tariffs. And that would be true. And they can also blame it on the war. And where did that come from? Trump. Trump started the war. Trump imposed the tariffs. And all the Republicans supported him. So they own this mess. And so they're going to be held accountable at the polls.
Speaker 1: did you know that september is world alzheimer's month most people treat their brain the way governments treat their balance sheets they don't look until something's already broken that's not how i operate i wanted to look at my own data and start tracking my numbers before things like brain fog became something i just accepted as normal so i went through function
Speaker 1: Your focus and mental stamina leave a data trail in your blood and Function tracks it, like omega-3 index, which is tied to focus and how your brain performs day to day. And homocysteine, when that number runs high, it's linked to brain fog and a higher risk of cognitive decline down the road. And if you want to go further, Function offers an Alzheimer's detection test,
Speaker 1: blood markers that can flag risk years before you'd ever notice a symptom. Check your brain and health the way I do. Function provides 160 plus lab tests for $1 a day and member pricing on advanced imaging. Join at functionhealth.com/Peter and use code Peter25 for a $25 credit. But going to trade,
Speaker 5: today is the day that the Canadian tariffs
Speaker 5: on American goods. These are the reciprocal tariffs because they were responding to Trump's tariff escalation. So these tariffs have kicked in and they're anywhere from 15%, 25% and
is up
Speaker 5: to 50% on
Speaker 4: various products. But they're focused on steel and aluminum,
dairy
Speaker 8: products, appliances,
Speaker 8: agricultural equipment, pulp and paper,
Speaker 5: plastics, and electronics.
Speaker 4: Now, why did Canada choose the particular products? It's about 20 billion of U.S. exports that are going to be subject to these tariffs. Well,
Speaker 5: And Canada was at least being somewhat selective. Again, I don't think they should have imposed these tariffs at all because the tariffs are on Canadians. They're not on Americans. So, you know, because Trump decided to punish Americans who buy Canadian goods, that doesn't mean
Speaker 6: that Carney should punish Canadians who want to buy American goods. I mean, how did two wrongs make a right? Right? Apparently in a trade war, they do. But at
Speaker 5: least...
Speaker 5: What Carney did is focus on products that could most easily be substituted for a Canadian-produced good or an import from another
Speaker 1: country. Now, sure, these goods will end up costing Canadians a little bit more, but not as much as the tariffs.
Speaker 1: So maybe they end up
Speaker 5: paying 5% more to avoid these 25% tariffs or whatever. I don't know the exact numbers.
But for
Speaker 5: products where there wasn't a, you know, economically viable easy substitute, he was smart enough to leave those alone. But where it was easy for Canada to
Speaker 1: compete or where Canada could source money,
Speaker 1: The goods from South America, from Europe, for Asia, it put the tariffs there. So the impact
is also going
Speaker 5: to be felt very strongly by American companies if they can't sell these goods up in Canada.
Speaker 6: Now, they're going to have to find some other market to sell into if they can't sell into their market of
Speaker 5: choice.
Speaker 5: Canada. So there are going
to be
Speaker 5: companies, individual companies in the
Speaker 6: U.S., they get harmed. But America is not going to win the trade war with Canada. In fact, we're not going to win any trade wars. Look at the news that came out, I think just today, China reported their trade numbers.
Speaker 6: And remember, China
Speaker 5: is the big boogeyman, right? The big enemy that Trump was targeting for its sin of having a big trade surplus.
And so China
Speaker 1: is the main target. And the highest tariffs really still are on Chinese goods. So China reported a great number on exports. August, most recent, Chinese exports rose 25% year over year.
Speaker 1: Imports also up 28 percent. So their imports went up. But their trade surplus for the month was one hundred nineteen billion dollars. It's basically the mirror image of America's. In fact, it's actually bigger. China actually runs a bigger monthly surplus in merchandise than we run a deficit, although sometimes we do have deficits in.
Speaker 1: North of 100 billion.
So
Speaker 7: in some ways, it really is just the mirror image. And but
in
Speaker 1: addition to that, China's exports with
Speaker 6: the U.S. rose 34 percent year over year
and
Speaker 1: year to date.
Speaker 1: China's already got an $806 billion surplus and they are on pace to have their biggest year ever, a record year for the
size of
Speaker 1: China's trade surplus.
Now, the
Speaker 1: interesting part is the record that they would beat the year that China had its biggest trade surplus in history was last year, 2025.
Speaker 1: Trump was president for all but about, what, two to three weeks of that year? And, you know, his signature campaign promise was to reduce the trade deficit with China. Yet we had a record high trade deficit. Now, maybe Trump could talk about, oh, he did reduce it in
Speaker 2: 2026, because if we extrapolate the year-to-date trade deficit with China in 2026, it's going to be below the,
Speaker 8: where it was in 2025. But it's still gonna be our fourth worst year ever. Now, number two and number three, worst years ever were 2024 and I think
Speaker 1: 2023. So those were under Biden. But Biden inherited these massive trade deficits from Trump because even during Trump's first term,
Speaker 1: our trade deficits went up. Trump handed Biden a bigger trade deficit than the one Obama handed Trump. So rather than winning on trade, we lost even bigger on trade during Trump's first term, and we're gonna lose even more during his second term. But what Trump did manage to achieve with the tariffs is our deficit,
Our
Speaker 1: bilateral
Speaker 7: deficit with
Speaker 2: China did drop. I mean, I think it was about maybe 30 percent or something like that. So by making Chinese goods more expensive, Americans bought fewer Chinese
Speaker 1: goods. You
know, if China had
Speaker 1: absorbed the tariffs, that wouldn't have happened. If Chinese goods hadn't gotten more expensive because the Chinese ate the tariffs by lowering their prices or by lowering the exchange rate of the yuan,
then
Speaker 1: Americans wouldn't have bought fewer Chinese products. The only reason we bought fewer Chinese products is because China didn't pay the
Speaker 7: tariffs. Americans were expected to pay the tariffs, just like I paid my tariffs. I went over a last podcast. I
Speaker 1: got a product imported from Europe and then FedEx sent me a bill for the tariff.
And
Speaker 1: then they sent me, and in the bill was more money they charged me to process the tariff.
Speaker 7: They didn't send the bill to the producer in Europe. They didn't say, hey, you know, you got to pay this tariff that we had to charge Peter Schiff, European company. You need to send us more money. No, they sent the bill to me. They didn't send the bill to the producer. I got the bill, the American consumer. And again,
the.
Speaker 7: Not only did I pay the tariff 100%, I paid the extra cost to process the tariff. So if there was no tariff, there would have been no processing fee. I would have just got the FedEx package and that would have been the end of it. Instead, I get a FedEx package and the next day I get a bill for the tariffs and for the tariff processing
Speaker 2: fee. But the trade deficit with China,
Speaker 2: went down because Chinese goods got more expensive for Americans. Now, what did I say was going to happen? I'm not talking about what happened after the fact. I predicted
Speaker 1: it before the fact. I said that China was going to be fine because it was a big world out there and if Americans
Speaker 5: couldn't afford to buy Chinese products, somebody else would happily buy them instead of us.
Speaker 5: See, Trump kept saying, we got all
Speaker 6: the cards, like we're the biggest consumer. Anybody can consume. The easiest thing you can do is be a consumer. I mean, anybody who has a family, you have any kids, do they have problems consuming? No, they consume everything. They don't produce. All they do is consume. If you're married, if you have a non-working spouse, I mean, my wife is a great consumer. She's consuming every single day.
Speaker 6: But the hard part is to earn the money
that she spends, to
Speaker 6: earn the money that my kids spend because they don't earn anything, right? And so I kept saying
Speaker 1: that this is nonsense. The cards are held by the producer. That is the hard part in the whole transaction. Consuming is easy, producing is
hard.
The
Speaker 1: reason poor countries are poor, it's not because they lack consumers. Their poor people would consume as much as we did if they had the production. It's supply that creates demand because supply transforms demand
Speaker 6: into actual purchasing power. Remember, in the science of economics, demand
is basically unlimited. There's no
Speaker 1: limit to what people want. People want everything.
People
Speaker 1: want stuff they don't even know that they want until somebody invents it. Then they can't live without it. So that's the easy part.
The
Speaker 6: hard part is producing.
Because you can't
Speaker 6: consume what hasn't been produced.
But once
Speaker 6: it's been produced, anybody can consume it.
Quick
Speaker 1: question. Are you hiring in another country right now? Because once you do, things can get complicated fast, but that's where Pebble can help. You can send offers in minutes to anyone in the world and get them onboarded fast. I've dealt with this firsthand. Once you start working with contractors and employees in different countries, suddenly you're juggling local labor laws, contracts, payroll, compliance issues, tax questions, and you're stitching together three or four different tools just to stay organized. It eats up time and it introduces is risk. That's where Pebble comes in. Pebble is an AI-powered global HR platform built
Speaker 1: for founders and operators who are hiring around the world. It lets you hire, pay, and manage talent in over 185 countries with onboarding that can be done in minutes. Instead of bouncing between separate systems for contracts, payroll, benefits, and compliance, Pebble brings everything together in one place, built-in guidance and local expertise so you don't have to become an HR lawyer just to expand your team internationally.
Speaker 1: The fastest growing companies are using Pebble to stay organized and reduce risk. Bottom line, it simplifies global people operations so you can focus on growing the business instead of worrying about paperwork. Their new standard discounted pricing at 399 US dollars per month per employee helps you contain costs. Go to highpebble.ai to get a free estimate. That's highpebl.ai for a free estimate. Now the reason Americans were consuming is because we were
Speaker 5: outbidding everybody with our strong dollar.
But by
Speaker 5: imposing tariffs,
Speaker 6: it made it harder for Americans to outbid because we now had to bid even more
because
Speaker 1: of the tariff and we couldn't afford it. And
so I
Speaker 1: said, well, that China's just gonna trade with other countries and that's what it's doing. That's why China has a record trade surplus now, even though it's trading less with the United States, it enjoys a smaller surplus
Speaker 1: with America. I mean, it's still got a surplus. It's not like it's got a deficit with us. No. It just has a smaller surplus than the one I had before. So we're still losing with China. But China is just winning bigger with other countries. Now, the real winners, I think, are the consumers in those countries who now got to buy Chinese goods that they couldn't buy before because Americans were buying them. We're the losers. We've lost out on those goods. But what have Americans done?
Speaker 1: it's not like we're producing the goods that we used to buy from China. No, we're just buying them from someplace else. Because if you look at America's trade deficit, so in 2025, our trade deficit was actually worse than it was in 2024. Got worse, despite the tariffs, right? It got worse. Now it's improved a little bit so far in 2026.
Speaker 7: Although who knows, right? We still got many months to go. But if you extrapolate,
Speaker 7: the current rate for the rest of the year, it's going to be a little bit of an improvement. So our trade deficit in goods, and I'm not talking even about the
Speaker 1: unified deficit because I'm not talking about services. We've always had a surplus in services and Trump never really complained about that or obviously never acknowledged that or talked about that. Trump is focusing on merchandise, on goods.
And so we're going
Speaker 1: to have a slight improvement over last year's record bad year.
But
Speaker 6: it's minimal.
And what's
Speaker 6: happening is
Speaker 1: because the tariffs disproportionately increased the cost of Chinese goods, what Americans ended up doing is buying goods from other countries. We didn't start manufacturing stuff here. We didn't, you know, resource everything.
and
Speaker 1: start producing domestically the stuff that we can no longer afford from China. We just found other countries to buy from. Now, obviously, those other countries charge us more than what China was charging us, because if they charged us less, we would have been buying for those countries anyway. China was giving us the best deal. That's why we had such a big deficit with China.
but
Speaker 1: because of the tariffs, China couldn't give us the best deal anymore. So who loses there? The Americans. We have to now take the next best deal. And we did, and we paid higher prices. But we didn't go cold turkey on China, because in many cases, China was still the best deal, even with the tariff. That's how efficient China is. That's what a great deal we were getting.
Speaker 6: The prices were so low,
Speaker 6: That even with the tariffs, it was the best deal we could find. And so we kept buying those goods. That's why China's trade surplus didn't disappear. We still bought their goods. We just didn't buy as many, but we paid a lot more money to buy it. Now, obviously,
Speaker 1: some Americans didn't buy those Chinese goods, right? That's why the trade deficit with China went down. And now maybe they bought them from another country and just paid a little bit more. So they're losers.
Or maybe
Speaker 1: they just didn't buy at all.
Maybe
Speaker 5: the next best option was too expensive and they just went without, but
it was
Speaker 5: Americans that lost. So we lost the trade war with China. It's obvious that
Speaker 6: we lost that trade war.
We're gonna
Speaker 6: lose the trade war with Canada. We will lose a trade war with any nation that we declare war
on.
Speaker 6: Because we are the beneficiaries, yes, technically, it's better to have a
Speaker 1: surplus than a deficit because, you know, you're earning money, right? When you run a surplus, that's like a company operating at a profit, right? The nation made a profit. And what does a nation do with its surplus? It invests it. It can acquire capital
Speaker 2: in the other country. It can buy money.
Speaker 2: Land, productive land, property, commercial property, farmland. It can buy equities. It can buy stakes in businesses. It can do stuff. And then it can earn a return on the assets that it accumulates as a result
Speaker 1: of investing in surpluses. When you run deficits, what are you doing? You're selling off your assets. You're getting poorer. You're selling off your cows to buy imported land.
Speaker 1: But in the short run, that trade-off has a benefit in that you get to consume more. You get to live beyond your means. And that's all American politicians are focused on. That's what Trump is focused on. He doesn't care about the long term. That's all part of his spiel, the Trump show.
Speaker 1: He cares about goosing the numbers. He wants the numbers to look good while he's in office so he can take credit for that. And so if he imposes these tariffs, the immediate impact
on
Speaker 6: there is going to take away that short-term benefit because it's going to make the cost of living go up.
Speaker 6: It's gonna make consumer prices go up. And it's going to make interest rates go up. Those are the two things that are on everybody's
Speaker 5: mind. And of course, rising interest rates could make the value of your house go down, which Trump doesn't want, could make the stock market really go down. It hasn't so far because AI has kind of been goosing the stock
market.
Speaker 6: But so Trump can't win any trade wars. They're going to be lost, which is why more and more of these nations now,
you
Speaker 1: know, recognize that Trump is is really neutered when it comes to following through with all of these threats. Because they are going to
Speaker 5: harm the U.S. economy and they're going to harm the economy.
Speaker 6: Republicans' chances in the midterm elections. Now,
Speaker 1: yes, in the long run,
we need
Speaker 1: to reduce our trade deficits, but the way we need to reduce them is not through protectionism. And as I said
Speaker 6: from the very beginning, another way these protectionist tariffs backfire is they undermine the productivity of American companies by making their imported components
too expensive. And so that
Speaker 6: puts them at a competitive disadvantage. And so we end up harming our own manufacturers. Yes,
Speaker 5: some specific companies benefit, but at the expense of others who lose. But even the companies that benefit, let's say that we have tariffs on steel
so that US
Speaker 5: steel manufacturers
can make extra
Speaker 5: profits.
Speaker 5: And maybe pay their steel workers higher wages because they could charge more money for their steel.
Speaker 1: Well, if U.S. car manufacturers now have to pay more for their steel, then they're not going to be as competitive. Certainly when it comes to exporting
Speaker 5: their cars to Europe or Asia. I mean, maybe they could still be somewhat competitive in the U.S.,
to
Speaker 5: the extent that we have tariffs on foreign automobiles that are coming in. But without those tariffs, the foreign automobiles will be cheaper because
Speaker 1: they'll be made with steel that wasn't subject to the tariffs. But if we've got to export our cars that were made with expensive steel, it's going to be harder to compete with companies that pay lower prices for that. So we end up harming our auto industry. And in the end, if the auto industry is smaller because of expensive steel,
Speaker 1: then U.S. steel companies have fewer domestic customers for their steel. So it could end up even hurting the steel companies. And in fact, you know, we've had all this protectionism on steel, yet we're a fraction of what we used to be when it comes to steel. We were a much bigger producer of steel in the 1950s than we are now. So the tariffs and a lot of the things that have happened have just contributed to the decline in an industry that we –
Speaker 1: that we once dominated. So what's happening with Canada, we're gonna lose that, right? Just like we're losing the war with Iran and like we lost the trade war with China.
And
Speaker 2: what is the collateral damage? Again, it's a loss of confidence in the U.S., in
Speaker 5: our ability to get our fiscal house
in order,
Speaker 5: in the credit worthiness
of
Speaker 2: the United States. And it's not just that interest
Speaker 1: rates are going up because of inflation. I mean, that's a good part of the problem.
But look at
Speaker 2: what's going on now. And I talk about this with the CapEx boom in
AI. Yeah.
And
Speaker 2: the hyperscalers, these companies, the big hyperscalers, Meta and Google and Amazon, all these companies had all this cash.
And they were
Speaker 6: parking it in U.S. Treasuries. So they were loaning their money to the U.S. government. They're
not doing
Speaker 6: that anymore. They blew through their cash. They bought computer stuff with it. And
they
Speaker 1: spent it all.
And
Speaker 1: now they're borrowing they're borrowing hundreds of billions of dollars from the same savings
Speaker 6: pool that the U.S. government is is is dipping into and the same pool that all the other governments that need to borrow money are dipping into. And
so the
Speaker 6: demand is growing and it's going to continue to grow. And
the
Speaker 1: thing is, as long as these companies believe that.
that
Speaker 1: they can generate these enormous returns based on borrowing money and building out data centers
or
Speaker 6: other AI infrastructure, they don't care what the rate is. They don't care if they have to pay 9%, 10%, 11%. They'll pay it because they believe they're gonna get this massive return. So the government's gonna have to
Speaker 1: compete with these companies.
Speaker 1: Because it's not risk-free. Not at all. You know, ironically, there's one product that the government makes that's risk-free. And that's the nickel. The U.S. nickel. Because copper prices are
as high
Speaker 1: as they are right now.
And because
Speaker 1: nickel prices are as high as they are right now. Now, the nickel used to be made 100% of nickel. But...
They
Speaker 5: stopped that because the nickel was too expensive. So they're now 75% copper and 25% nickel. But
with the
Speaker 5: current price of copper and nickel, each
nickel is
Speaker 6: worth 7.76 cents. That's 55% above the face value.
You
Speaker 6: could go to a bank today and you can give them $2 and they'll
Speaker 1: give you a roll of 40 nickels, assuming they haven't run out. They don't mark it up. You just pay $2 for 40 nickels and you've got more than $3 worth of copper and nickel for your $2. That is
a can't lose
Speaker 1: investment because you pay $2 for over $3 worth of copper and nickel. It'll
never be
Speaker 1: worth less than $2. So you can't lose.
Speaker 1: Even if copper and nickel prices crash, if they crash 90%, you still got $2 face value of nickels. Now, I don't think that's going to happen, but even if it did, you can't lose. Now, yes, you're not going to get any interest on your nickels if you put them in a safety deposit box, but you can't lose your principal.
On the other
Speaker 1: hand, what if nickel and copper prices keep rising?
You
Speaker 1: already are leveraged because you're getting $3 worth of nickel and copper for $2. So if nickel and copper prices go up by a third, 33%, you've doubled your money. Now you've got $4 worth of nickel for your $2. You've got a highly leveraged nickel and copper play that costs you no risk.
Speaker 1: I mean, that is the risk-free return. It kicks the hell out of U.S. Treasuries. Who wants a four or 5% return on Treasuries where inflation can wipe you out? Inflation is not gonna wipe you out if you own copper and nickel, it's just gonna go up. Now, I know there are people that say, "But Peter, you can't, it's illegal to melt them down." Which is true. But it's illegal to melt down dimes and quarters for their silver content, yet that doesn't stop those prices from rising.
Speaker 1: Um, I, I think, at least I think it's illegal. Um, but you know, shift gold, we sell, you know, bags, junk, silver, we sell dimes and quarters and nickels. I'm going to check if
Speaker 5: it's illegal. Hold on. But the thing is you don't have to melt them down. Oh no. Okay. So it is legal. You can melt down the silver and dime. So
I
Speaker 2: guess they, they, they passed the special rule.
Speaker 2: to say you couldn't melt down pennies and nickels because they knew that otherwise that's what would happen. So it is illegal, but they outlawed the penny. So they don't even make, or they didn't outlaw it, but they stopped making pennies for general circulation late last year.
The penny,
Speaker 2: though, is not nearly as good a deal as the nickel because the penny right now has about 1.2%.
Speaker 2: 0.07 cents worth of copper and zinc. It's mostly zinc now. If you have an old penny that was minted before 1982, so 1981 or earlier,
Speaker 1: that's 90% copper. Those pennies are worth almost four and a half cents. So if you happen to grab one of those, I mean, they're still circulating. Most of them are out of circulation now. But if you grab one of those pennies, put it aside because it's going to be worth a dime
Speaker 1: uh relatively soon so so hold on to it but the nickel is a better deal obviously if you get an old nickel that's all nickel i forget the value there it's a lot higher but even the new modern nickel the ones they're still making i have 7.6 cents worth of metal in them i think they're going to stop making these probably in another year or two they're gonna they're gonna stop making the nickel because for the same reason they stopped making the penny it's too expensive i mean it costs to the
Speaker 6: government.
Speaker 6: you know, probably eight cents to make a nickel, right? I mean, that's probably one of the biggest wasteful expenditures. I mean, why would you spend eight cents to make five, right? But that's what
Speaker 1: they do. But that's why they stopped with the penny.
But it doesn't
Speaker 1: matter. Even if it's illegal
to melt
Speaker 1: them down, the metal is still there. And so they're still worth their weight because most people don't melt down their money.
Speaker 1: silver coins and their dimes, nickels, and quarters. They don't melt them down. That's why the bags are still there because people use it as a recognizable way of owning silver. Well, the same thing is going to happen with nickel. People will own nickels for the same reason. But of course, criminals are not going to care. So I'm sure there will be an underground market
Speaker 1: in nickels. Criminals
Speaker 2: will buy nickels illegally. I mean, it's not illegal to buy them. They'll take them and they will illegally melt them down and then they will sell the nickel and the copper. I mean, because once it's melted down, I mean, how the hell do you know where the copper came from or where the nickel came from? And I don't know that the
FBI or
Speaker 2: the CIA
Speaker 1: is going to waste a lot of resources trying to find illegal smelting operations going on. I mean, they got bigger fish to fry.
Speaker 1: there's so much going on with drugs or other illegal activity that they're trying to clamp down on. But criminals are going to have no problem with doing this. To say, oh, just because it's illegal, no one's going to do it. I mean, if the government could stop crime by passing laws, there'd be no crime. Obviously, criminals don't care about the law. That's why they're criminals. So nickels are going to be a great investment. There will
Speaker 2: be a black market in people who are legally melting them down but even if they're not melted down but but that's
Speaker 1: That's really the best deal the government is giving you because U.S. Treasuries, inflation is going to wipe those out. And you can say, yeah, there's no downside in Treasuries because you're going to get your money back. Well, that's the same with nickels. You're going to get your nickel back.
Speaker 1: But you've already got 50% worth of appreciation. So how many years are you
going to
Speaker 1: have to clip a 5% coupon to get a 50% return? That's
quite a
Speaker 1: few years. But by the time you get that money, inflation will have eroded away the value of your treasuries. Meanwhile, five years from now, who knows what these nickels are going to be worth? Because nickel prices are going to keep going up. Copper prices are going to keep going up. All prices are going to keep going up because the government is going to keep creating inflation.
Speaker 2: because politically they've got no they've got no alternative they can't accept the reality that's why I don't believe that the Fed is going to hike rates next week now what I believe
Speaker 7: the strategy
is to talk
Speaker 7: about raising rates act as if you're going to raise rates but never actually do
just
Speaker 7: like Trump. Talk as if you're going to do all these things and just don't follow through. Talk like you're going to bomb Iran back to the Stone Age and then come up with a reason not to do it. So the Fed is always going to have a reason why they didn't hike rates this time. You know, there was some number or something that gave them hope that it looks like inflation is trending down to two percent. But don't worry.
Speaker 7: Don't worry if it comes in too hot. We're ready. We're ready to raise rates. Trust us. We will. We'll do it. We're serious, right? We're going to hike rates and then not do it. Because the real problem is what does the Fed buy with a 25 basis point rate hike? Nothing. They're going to get nothing from that. It's not going to do anything about inflation because it's too little. The rate
hikes need
Speaker 7: to be a lot bigger than 25 basis points. And in fact,
Speaker 7: If the Fed does hike by 25
Speaker 6: basis points, what is the market going to think? Oh, that's it? No, they're going to start pricing in the next 25 basis point rate hike. So if the Fed hikes rates 25 basis points, it's going to have to do it again.
Speaker 1: It's going to be in the same predicament that it's in now. Only rates will be even higher, which means...
Speaker 1: Bigger problem for stocks, bigger problem for real estate, bigger problem for the federal debt. We're spending over $1.2 trillion per year on interest on the national debt now.
And that's
Speaker 1: going to keep rising. By the time Trump leaves office, it's going to be $2 trillion. And that's if rates just stay where they are, just based on all the debt that has
Speaker 2: to roll over and all the new debt. We're borrowing over $3 trillion a year. So over the next two and a
Speaker 1: half years, that's another, what, $7, $8 trillion. That's why I've said that there's a chance that if we go through a more serious recession in the second half of Trump's term, we could hit $50 trillion on the national debt.
Speaker 1: before Trump finishes. It's 40, you know, just over 40 now. But even
the
Speaker 2: way it's projected, I think the official projections probably show it at about
Speaker 1: 47 trillion by the time he finishes. So we've got to pay interest on that extra 7 trillion that we're not paying interest on at all. Plus we got to pay extra interest on all of those notes and bonds that mature between now and then.
Speaker 1: That we're paying maybe 50
Speaker 2: basis points in interest now because the money was borrowed when rates were really low and now we have to refinance it when the rates are much higher. And if the Fed actually does hike interest rates, then it compounds that problem. And we'll
Speaker 1: see what happens. We're going to get more inflation data on Thursday
Speaker 2: and Friday. We're going to get the PPI on Thursday and the CPI.
Speaker 2: on, on Friday. And those numbers could easily come out much hotter than expected. And if they are look out, uh, because there could be some serious carnage in the bond market. Uh,
and
Speaker 1: then in the stock market, we'll see what happens with the precious metals market, because what they typically do is go down. Like gold was down about 40 bucks today. And I think the main reason was the pressure being put on goal or down 46 bucks, closed at $4,350.
Speaker 1: But the pressure was building from the weakness in the bond market and the strength in the oil
Speaker 2: market and in the copper market, which was, you know, pushing up the odds of a rate hike next week. But we'll see how gold reacts to the hot inflation numbers if we get them.
But
Speaker 2: ironically, if we get colder numbers, gold is going to soar if we get lower than expected, because that's going to take the rate hikes completely off the table if they're even on the table in the first place, which I don't really think they are. But if we get, you know, cooler inflation numbers, which will still be bad, just not
as bad
Speaker 2: as they expect.
Speaker 2: Then we could get a big move and the odds of a hike in September will come crashing down because the Fed will have the exact excuse that it's been looking for. But if it's not that excuse, they'll come up with another one because
Speaker 1: they don't want to hike rates. And Trump made that clear. I mean, Trump is still demanding that the Fed cut rates and even threatening to harm the economy if it doesn't. So I will be talking about those things.
Speaker 1: numbers on Friday. I'll try to do the podcast pretty much right after the market closes because Friday is going to be Rosh Hashanah. It's Jewish New Year, which starts at sundown. So I got to get the podcast done before sun goes down because I got plans to observe the holiday that evening. It's also going to be the 25th anniversary. I don't like to use that word because it's
Speaker 2: anniversary again. That's a good thing. But it'll be 25 years
Speaker 2: Uh, since, uh, the nine 11, 2001, 25 years, it's hard to believe so much time has passed, uh, since that horrible incident, uh, from 25 years ago, but that will be that day, but I will
do a
Speaker 2: podcast on Friday. And, uh, there's probably going
to be a
Speaker 2: lot that's going to happen between now and then. Uh, so make sure and listen in the meantime, in the meantime,
If you
Speaker 2: want to get nickels, you don't need shift gold for that. You could just pick them up at the bank. But if you have bigger money, you want to buy gold and silver before the next big move up. You want to go to shift gold. And as I said on last week's podcast, open up your T-gold account now. Get it funded. Put some money in there so you're ready to go when we roll out the gold-backed debit cards today.
Speaker 2: the secured credit cards to allow you to borrow against your gold if you need to at low interest rates. But those products are coming, and they're the first of many, so you've got to make sure that you are at T-gold. And if you're not reading our letters at Shift Sovereign, make sure and subscribe and start reading our content. Just make sure it's on your to-do list. We're putting out
a lot
Speaker 2: of really good stuff, And I'm looking forward to seeing some of our subscribers.
Speaker 2: is what it's about two weeks now we're all sold out uh for the uh shift sovereign plan b event in in uh in panama city uh on i think it's september uh 18th through the 20th i think those are the dates it's going to fall right between uh rosh Hashanah and yom kippur and i'm looking forward to spending yom kippur we're going to spend it in panama city with the mayor who's also Jewish, happens to be a fan of mine. He will be at our conference.
And
Speaker 2: we're going to experience the Jewish culture of Panama. You know, for the last couple of years, Panama has been the number one destination for expats, the number one country to live. And for good reason. I really liked it the first time I was there and looking forward to coming back and seeing some of the subscribers to Shift Sovereign at our Plan B conference. And again, remember to subscribe to my YouTube channel, like this video and leave a comment. And perhaps I will reply to your comment. Bye for now.